A Guide to the Angus William McDonald Papers, 1860
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Angus William McDonald Papers, 1860
The Library of Virginia
21877
18 leaves, negative photostats
Angus William McDonald
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Rose McDonald, June 1941.
Biographical Information
Angus McDonald was born 14 February 1799 in Winchester, Virginia, to Angus McDonald (1769-1814) and Mary McGuire (d. 1809). He attended Old Winchester Academy and was appointed to the United States Military Academy 30 June 1814. Graduating 17 July 1817, McDonald was appointed 3rd lieutenant and eventually rose to the rank of 1st lieutenant. He resigned his commission 31 January 1819. He surveyed lands in Illinois and Missouri with his brother Edward Charles McDonald (1803-1862), then became a partner in the Missouri Fur Company in 1821. When the company failed, McDonald returned to Virginia, settling in Hampshire County, where he became deputy sheriff. One 11 January 1827 he married Leacy Ann Naylor (d. 1843) of Hampshire County. After her death, he married Cornelia Peake (1822-1909) of Missouri. McDonald relocated to Winchester 9 September 1856. Two years later, 26 March 1858, Governor Henry A. Wise (1806-1876) appointed him a commissioner for Virginia in a boundary dispute with Maryland. In 1860, McDonald travelled to England with his son William Naylor McDonald (1834-1895) to get copies of records held by the British government. He returned and was in Richmond, Virginia, when the state seceded from the Union. He went to Harper's Ferry and raised a regiment of cavalry for service. After seeing active military duty early in the Civil War, he returned to Richmond and became a military advisor in the War Department. Because of illness, he travelled to Lexington, Virginia, to be with his wife in December 1863. The following June, Union troops captured McDonald and he was imprisoned until released on 7 November 1864. He returned to Richmond, where he died 1 December 1864 and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, June-October 1860, of Angus McDonald (1799-1864) of Winchester, Virginia, who was a commissioner on a boundary dispute between Virginia and Maryland and who travelled to England to collect documents concerning Virginia's boundaries. Papers include receipts and accounts concerning the copying of documents; letters to and from McDonald and William Naylor McDonald (1834-1895) concerning their trip to England for documents, personal and family matters, and the shipment of documents back to Virginia; and notes on items to be copied.
Contents List
- Letter, 7 June 1860, from Angus McDonald to the president of the North Atlantic Steamship Company concerning the shipment of a box of records.
- Letter, 1 July 1860, from William Naylor McDonald (1834-1895) in London to his sisters Susan Leacy McDonald (1839-1930) and Flora McDonald (1842-1930) of Winchester, Virginia, describing his stay in London.
- Receipt, September 1860, from Charles Booth to Angus McDonald for payment for copies made.
- Account, 6 September 1860, of S. Williams with Angus McDonald for copies made.
- Letter, 19 September 1860, from Angus McDonald to Beverley Tucker discussing business.
- Letter, 25 September 1860, from Susan Leacy McDonald to Angus McDonald discussing events at home.
- Receipt, 29 September 1860, from W. Thompson to Angus McDonald for payment for copies made.
- Account, 6 October 1860, of Charles Booth with Angus McDonald for copies made.
- Account, 9 October 1860, of A. A. Burt with Angus McDonald for copies made.
- Receipt, 25 October 1860, from Thomas Stanley to Angus McDonald for bookbinding.
- Letter, no date, from Angus McDonald to an unknown recipient (which may be the remainder of 7 June 1860 letter).
- Notes, no date, on items to be copied and inserted.